<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A modest discourse concerning the ceremonies heretofore used in the Church of England, shewing the unlawfulness of them in the worship of God.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89214</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867966</idno>
  <idno type="VID">168930</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240956519</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2361</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1035_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209061</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867966</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99867966e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89214)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168930)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 153:E1035[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A modest discourse concerning the ceremonies heretofore used in the Church of England, shewing the unlawfulness of them in the worship of God.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 33 [i.e. 41], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by T.R. for Nathanael Webb, at the Kings-head in St. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 28".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Church of England --  Customs and practices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168930:1"/>
            <p>A MODEST DISCOURSE Concerning the Ceremonies Heretofore used in the CHURCH of ENGLAND, Shewing the unlawfulness of them in the worship of GOD.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. R.</hi> for <hi>Nathanael Webb,</hi> at the <hi>Kings-head</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:168930:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168930:2"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE Concerning the Ceremonies Heretofore used in the CHURCH of ENGLAND, Shewing the unlawfulness of them in the worship of God.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Ceremonies of <hi>Crosse, Surplice, Kneeling in the Sacraments,</hi> enjoyned to be used in the administration of Gods worship, seems to me unlawfull to be used therein for these reasons.</p>
            </argument>
            <div n="1" type="reason">
               <p n="1">1 <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rom the ground whereupon they are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned, the authority of the Church in commanding matters of indifferency, which wanteth ground from Scripture.</p>
               <p n="1">1. From the Commission of Christ; Christ gave Commission to his Apostles to teach his people, to observe all things, whatsoever
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168930:3"/>he had commanded them, <hi>Matthew</hi> 28.20. The authority which the Church hath received from Christ, is not judicial, to make lawes or Canons of such things, which he hath left free, but ministeriall only, to declare his lawes and statutes unto the people, as may appear. Things commanded them by Christ, must be therefore the Subject of their teaching. If they teach things not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, they go beyond the bounds of their commission, which for commissioners of an earthly Prince to do, were the incurring of a <hi>Premanire,</hi> and what were it lesse than sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious usurpation in the commissioners of Christ.</p>
               <p n="2">2. From the practise of the Apostles, who laid no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther burthen upon the disciples than necessary things. <hi>Act.</hi> 15.28. necessary I say, though not all of them in themselves, by vertue of any command of God, forbidding them gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally to all Churches, at all times, but by reason of the present offence, which that time the weake <hi>Jew</hi> would take at the eating of bloud, and strangled, and the weake <hi>Gentiles,</hi> at the eating of things sacrificed to Idols. In which regard the royall law of love, requiring that nothing be done to the offence of our weake brethren; and the Apostles wisely discerning that in the Churches of those times, the eating of such things would be offensive to weak bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, they therefore, warrantably concluded and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the name of the holy ghost, as well as of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seves, abstinence from such things, when the same thing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward ceased to be offensive, abstinence from them ceased to be necessary, yea, and the Apostles ordinance touching that abstinence ceased to be in force. The Christians abstaining from bloud, a long time after, in the primitive Church, when the offence of the <hi>Jew</hi> ceased, was yet a seasonable preventing of the scandall, or rather slander of the <hi>Gentile,</hi> for when the <hi>Gentiles</hi> accused them of unnaturall feeding of mans flesh and bloud in sacrifices: how fitly did <hi>Tertullian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> plead that it was incredible they should defile themselves by eating of mans bloud, who held the eating of any bloud unlawfull, by the rules of their religion.</p>
               <p>But the practise of <hi>Paul</hi> in this kind excelleth, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168930:3"/>to commend to the Churh of <hi>Corinth</hi> single life, which was not onely a thing indifferent in its own nature, but also of much expediency to them in regard of the present per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutions and other continuall worldly cares, <hi>ver.</hi> 26, 29. yet because he had received no commandment from the Lord to impose this estate of single life upon them; therefore he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self giveth no Commandment unto them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.6. but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vise only as one that had obtained mercy from the Lord to be faithfull, <hi>ver.</hi> 25. and yet lest this advice should seem to bind too farre, even to the prejudice of the use of their Christian liberty in the ordinance of marriage, he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore telleth them what he speaketh in this kind, he would be so understood as to speake for their commodity, and not to entangle them in a snare, ver. 35 and therefore if they shall see marriage needfull for themselves, or their virgins, and shall thinke the want of marriage uncomely, he giveth them leave (notwithstanding his advice) to do what they will, <hi>ver.</hi> 36. so that in the carriage of this busines, there appeareth evidently to excell in <hi>Paul</hi> a double care. First lest he should seem tomake an ordinance or to give a commandment to the Church in such things of indifferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, whereof he received no commandment from the Lord. Secondly lest he should seem by making any such ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to prejudice the use of Christian liberty. Thirdly from the Apostles reproofe of the <hi>Colossians,</hi> for suffering them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to be burthened with such things as did perish with the use of them, and were after the commandments of men, <hi>Colos.</hi> 2.20, 22. From which words of the Apostle a double reason may be gathered to prove the unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullnes of yeilding to Church-traditions of indifferency.</p>
               <p n="1">I. Such things as perish with the use of them (that is, leave no blessing behind them) why are you burthened with them?</p>
               <p>But ceremonies of indifferency perish with the use of them, making the worship in hand, never awhit the better by the use of them, nor never awhit the worse by forbearing of them, therefore ceremonies of indifferency why are you bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened with them?</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:168930:4"/>
               <p n="2">II. Such things as have no higher warrant than the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of men, why are you burthened with them?</p>
               <p>But Ceremonies of indifferency have no higher warrant than the Commandments of men, therefore why are you burthened with them?</p>
               <p>And indeed this semeth to me amongst many other, one perpetual difference to be kept, between the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God and man: God may first command a thing, and then it becometh good; man must first see a thing good, and then command it.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>It will be said, when Christ limited the Apostles Commission to the teaching only of such things to be observed as himself hath commanded; he meant only to restrain them to the teaching of such things as necessary to salvation, or as binding the Conscience, or as parts of Gods worship; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when the false Apostles urged the observation of Jewish Ceremonies as necessary to salvation, and with opinion of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, the Apostle justly reasoneth against them, by shewing their end to be anprofitable (they perishing with the use) and their authority to be of men only. But setting aside the opinion of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity, and of worship, Christ never forbad it, nor the Apostles never reproved it, that the Church should institute Ceremonies, which Christ commanded not as, matters of indifferency, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> Though it be true that the false Apostles put ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity and worship in their Ceremonies, which made them so much the worse, yet some of the reasons used by the Apostle, do strike also at their indifferency (they perishing with the use) and at their authority, they proceeding only from the Counsell and will of man, being after the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments and doctrines of men: so, that howsoever the Apostles principal scope, was to reprove their Ceremonies of some more gross superstition than is hitherto found in ours, with us yet the force of his reasons (<hi>ver.</hi> 22.) condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth them likewise of some such faultiness, as is common to theirs, with ours also, (to wit) indifferency, and dependence upon humane authority. Neither is it enough to say, that Christ, when he limited the Apostles to the teaching of things
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168930:4"/>commanded by him, spake only of teaching his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as matters of necessity, and gave leave to teach other matters of indifferency at their own discretion, unless it be shewen where Christ gave such leave to his Apostles or their successours so to do; that they ought to teach all things to be observed, which be commanded, is expressed in their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, but that they may teach other things to be observed, either as indifferent or necessary, which he commanded not, I see no warrant thereof, either from their Commission or from other Scripture, the place usually alledged for warrant, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. seemeth to me to afford no such liberty, <hi>Let all things be done decently and by order: (All things)</hi> I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand all the duties of gods worship: whether singing, or praying, or preaching, or speaking, or interpreting Tongues, or administring Sacraments, or Censures, as <hi>ver.</hi> 26. And the decency and order wherein all these things are to be done, I understand to be such, as whose contrary is undecent and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly: as, Let the <hi>Corinthian</hi> women pray with their heads covered, and the men with their heads uncovered, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out long hair, for these things are decent, and the (contrary thereof undecent: as, <hi>Judge in your selves,</hi> saith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, <hi>Is it comely that a woman pray unto God uncovered, or doth not nature it self teach you, that if a man have long hair it is a shame unto him,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.13, 14. And let the Prophets speak, two or three: and if any thing be revealed to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther standing by, let the first hold his peace, and the spirits of the Prophets let them be subject to the Prophets: these things all of them keep such comely order, as the doing contra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iwise were disorderly confusion. If all should speak at once, and the spirits of the Prophets should not submit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves one to another in the Lord, what disorder and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion would this be, beseeming not the Churches of the Saints, but the <hi>routs</hi> of <hi>Cyclops: ubi</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. So that it seemeth to me no part of the Apostles meaning to give liberty to the Church, to make Lawes or Canons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning matters of indifferency, but only to provide that no duty of Gods worship be offered up unto him in any sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full undecency and disorder, which will the better appear, if
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168930:5"/>we go about to conclude such Canons of indifferent things from the Apostles generall proposition. Say the Church should command all ministers to preach in a gowne, and should inferre this commandment from the Apostles generall rule, let all things be done decently. To preach in a gowne is decent, therefore let that be done, who se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not this conclusion to runne affirmatively in the second figure. And indeed that such kind of commandments are not grounded at all upon the commandment of the Apostle, appeareth also evidently from hence, that when such commandments of the Church are transgressed, yet the commandment of the Apostle is not transgressed, which could not be, if such commandments of the Church were grounded upon the commandment of the Apostle: for instance, if the church command me to preach in a gown, I preaching in a cloak transgresse indeed the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, but not at all the commandment of the Apostle, for he that preacheth in a cloak, preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth decently (which is all the Apostles commandment required) yea, and as decently as he that preacheth in a gowne, else whereto serves <hi>Tertullian</hi>'s whole book <hi>de Pallio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>Why, but may not the Church command all mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters to minister in the same kind of vestiments for unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie sake; Is not variety in this kind an undecent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans.</hi> No, uniformity in matters of indifferency God never required, but in such cases commanded for preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of unity and brotherly love, that no man should judge or despise his brother, and the strong to bear with the infirmities of the weake, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 13, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> 15.1, 2.</p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>But what direction of the Apostle was given when there was no Christian Magistrate?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans.</hi> True, but since God blessed Churches with Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian magistrates, it is not in their power to alter the lawes of God concerning this unitie and brotherly love, and the meanes of preserving the same. Nay, they themselves as Christians are bound to observe those directions of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168930:5"/>the Apostle in their own persons, yea and as magistrates to see that their subjects also observe the same.</p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>What, then may not the Church command the times of the day and places of Gods worship, which are matters of indifferency?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans.</hi> These things for ordinary course, may fully be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for without any commandment of the Church. Some congregations repaire to Churches, other to Chapells, some at eight of the cloke, some at nine, others at ten, but all of their owne accord, as may stand best with their Ministers occasions and the provision and business of the body of the parish: indeed when God calleth to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, either humiliation in a religious fast, or solemn rejoycing in a holy feast, the Church may then command the times of both, as in Christian discretion may be thought fittest for the vacancy of the congregation. But this is not to command a matter of indifferency: but to follow Gods calling in a point of duty.</p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>But did not</hi> Paul <hi>command a watter of indifferency, when he commanded greetings, with an holykisse. Is there a necessity of kissing whomsoever we greet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aus. Paul</hi> doth not command kissin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, but the holines of it, for whereas kissing was an usuall manner of salutation gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally throughout all most all countries, <hi>Paul</hi> in that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment provideth only, that the kisses given in way of salutation be not lascivious, or trea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rous, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plementall, but holy, expressing Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n affection, and thus though kissing be not necessary, yet where kissing is in use, the holinesse thereof commanded by the Apostle is necessary.</p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>If it be not in the power of the Church to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in matters of indifferency, how coul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the primitive Church take up such plenty of ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ions in this kind.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans.</hi> They tooke up those observations, not upon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of their church-governors, but partly voluntarily of their own accord, partly upon the example or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of some whom they much reverenced. <hi>Socr. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Cap.</hi> 22. <hi>Sozon l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 19.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:168930:6"/>
               <p n="2">2. The observations which themselves kept, they did not thrust upon others, but left every particular church free to their own discretion, <hi>Socr. ibid. Sozon ibid. Cypr. in Sententiis haereticorum, de haereticis, baptizandis. Victor</hi>'s immoderate zeale, in excommunicating them of <hi>Asia</hi> for their different observations of <hi>Easter,</hi> was censured by <hi>Cyprian</hi> and <hi>Irenaeus</hi> as stretching the rigor of his gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not only to persous beyond his line, but also to things or causes of indifferency, not admitting such severe censure, <hi>Euseb. l.</hi> 5.1.26.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is not to be forgotten with what a cloud of super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition, these indifferent observations in processe of time (by Gods just judgement) over-spread the face of the Church, so that men grew to put necessity in matters of indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency, and to put indifferency in matters of necessity, and in the end to observe the whole worship of God rather in a pompous dumb show of outward ceremony, than in any inward life of Spirit, and truth.</p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>But though it be granted that it is not in the power of the Church to command matters of indifferency, and therefore that the governors of the Church shall sin, if they do command things of this kind, yet neverthelesse, it may be thought to be no sin in private men to obey this commandment, for they herein do but exercise their lawfull liberty in using things of indifferency, as may stand best with their own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediency.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans.</hi> 1. It is denyed (and the deniall proved in the seq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>) that these are things of indifferency to be used (as is required) in the service of God, and so both they which command them, and they which use them, do both alike sin in so doing.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Though it be granted they are things of indifferency, yet if it be not in the power of the Church to command things of this nature, do we not in this case partake of our governors sin, if we obey their unlawfull command? For do not we build them up in this erroneous opinion of the lawfullnes of their commanding in such things, if ministers, especially of any number and nore, shall yeild
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168930:6"/>thereunto without contradiction? would not the Governors themselves leave off commanding and urging such things) if they did conceive they had no power from God to command herein? Is it not an offensive use of our liberty to endanger thereby the souls of our Governours?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="reason">
               <head>
                  <hi>REASON</hi> II.</head>
               <p>FRom the Rule of Gods Worship and of the whole man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of administration or performance thereof: Gods Worship call not only (according to the School) but also (according to the Scriptures) whatsoever we do (in way of reverent acknowledgement of his divine Excellency) im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately offer up unto God, as prayers, sacrifices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but we do offer from God in his Name unto his people, as preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Sacraments, <hi>&amp;c. Mat.</hi> 15.9. The manner of admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration of Gods worship (or as Divines are wont to call it) the circumstances of Gods worship, I call, whatsoever is set apart for the administration, or performance of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship; as the dayes, the places, the instruments, as the fire for the sacrifice, the Ministers, and their garments (though appointed but for comeliness and glory in their mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.40, 41. Now the Rule, as well of the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances of Gods worship, as of the worship it self, I take to be, not the Commandement of man, but the Word of God, <hi>Deut,</hi> 12.32. where the Lord forbiddeth, not only all Traditions and Constitutions of men added to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as the Rule of our faith and manners, nor only all such worship, which (for the substance of it) is not commanded in the Scriptures, but also all such circumstance or manner of performance of worship unto God, as is added, beside the direction of the Word, for these words are a conclusion of the who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Chapter, and gives direction, not only that they offer not up their children in sacrifice to God, as the Heathen did, <hi>ver.</hi> 31. (which kind of sacrifice he never commanded, but also that they offer not up the sacrifices commanded by him, neither in such places, not before such Images, nor in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168930:7"/>any such manner as the <hi>Gentiles</hi> used, <hi>ver.</hi> 2, 3, 4. no, nor yet in such place and sort as seemed good in their own eyes, <hi>ver.</hi> 8.13. but as well for the manner of performance of the worship, as for the worship it self, they should take heed to do whatsoever he commanded, without adding ought thereto or taking ought therefrom. Hence it was, that nothing was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by <hi>David</hi> or <hi>Solomon,</hi> touching Church-Musick, or the orders of the <hi>Levites</hi> (both which were but circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Gods worship) but according to the Commandment of the Lord by the hand of his Prophets, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 29.25. Hence <hi>David</hi> was taxed for attempting to build a Temple to God upon this ground, because God had not prevented him or any of the Judges, his Predecessours with a Commandment to that purpose, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.7. Hence <hi>Aarons</hi> Holy-day to the Lord, and <hi>Jeroboams</hi> feast of the eighth moneth were both of them taxed as the forgeries of their own heart, because God had required no such thing at their hands, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.5. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12.33. and in a word, as it fareth with these, so doth it with all the rest of the circumstances of Gods worship: if they be added beyond or beside the word of God, God not requiring them, doth not accept them, for the word of God being the Rule of Holiness, to appoint or use any holy thing without the warrant of the word, is to transgress the word. Now all these circumstances of Gods worship are holy to the Lord, as being set apart from common or civil use to the service of the Tabernacle, I mean, to the administration of religious worship unto God; for, whatsoever is set apart from common use, God hath set his property upon it, that it is now holy unto himself, <hi>Lev.</hi> 27.28. whence it was, that not only the garments which God appointed for <hi>Aaron</hi> and his sonnes to minister in, are call <hi>Holy,</hi> Exod. 28.2. but also the Censers of <hi>Corah</hi> and his Company are challenged by God as holy unto him, because they offered Incense in them before the Lord, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.38. Such seemeth to me the case of the <hi>Cross</hi> and <hi>Surplice,</hi> they being not permitted in common or civil use, but set apart for administration of Baptism and offering up prayer unto the Lord; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they must either have a word of institution in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168930:7"/>for the hallowing of them, which they have not, or else the Scriptures are impleaded not to be the perfect Rule of Holiness, which yet indeed they are.</p>
               <p>Say not, we put no holiness in a <hi>Cross</hi> or <hi>Surplice,</hi> but use them only as indifferent things for decencies sake: for though in word and judgement we deny holiness to these things, yet in very deed we hallow them by setting them apart to the administration of Gods holy worship. Gods Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the setting apart of any thing for himself, or for his service maketh not a thing holy, but truly and acceptably holy: mans setting any thing apart for God, or for his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice maketh it also holy, though superstitiously. When <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantine</hi> in honour of the Church at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> gave to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carius</hi> their Bishop a costly Vestment wrought with Gold wherein to administer Baptism; the Vestment was reputed an holy garment: yea, and is so called by <hi>Theodoret. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiast. Histo. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 27. And when <hi>Cyril</hi> was accused to have sold the same to a Stage-player, it stirred up great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation against him, as against some sacrilegious person; And is not our <hi>Surplice,</hi> though not so costly, yet as holy as that Vestment. If it be demanded then upon what warrant do Churches dedicate and set apart Temples and Dayes to God and his Worship.</p>
               <p>I answer, 1. That I know no warrant for the dedicating or setting apart either Temple or Day unto God, or to the duties of his Worship in these times of the New Testament, except those dayes which God calleth for as holy to himself, as the Lords Day, and a day of fasting when God calleth to solemn humiliation (<hi>Joel</hi> 1.14.) and an holy feast, when God by some extraordinary blessing calleth to solemn Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 30.23.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Because God giveth general warrant of assembling together to the duties of his worship in any place (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.8.) and at any time (2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2.) therefore, doubtless it is lawfull to assemble in Temples as well as in other places, and upon such dayes as are appointed by the Church as well as upon others: yea, and because Temples both for their largeness and thightness from injury of weather are more
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168930:8"/>expedient for the Congregation than other places, either without doors or of less capacity: therefore it is more seaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable for them to meet in Temples than elswhere, provided alwayes, 1. That the Temples be not esteemed Gods houses, but the Churches, as serving not him, but our selves with them, and the dayes be not esteemed as holy dayes to the Lord, but as assembly-dayes for the Congregation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That in such Temples, and on such dayes before, and after the administration of Gods worship, we do not restrain civil Assemblies, or Courts to be kept, and secular businesses to be transacted in them, for so indeed we do not set them apart for God, or for his worship, but use them indifferently for our own occasions, whether religious or civil. To shut up this whole second Argument: If the <hi>Cross</hi> and <hi>Surplice</hi> which are but circumstances of Gods worship be therefore unwarrantable, because they want institution from the word, how much more evidently will kneeling at the Sacrament appear unwarrantable, which is not a circumstance of Gods worship, but in it self a part of Gods worship, being one kind of external adoration, <hi>Psal.</hi> 95.6. Such worship of God as himself hath not required, he accepteth not, kneeling in the Sacrament is such a worship as God never required, how then can I hope it should be accepted? To worship God by kneeling in prayer, I find warranted by Commandement and example in Scripture: but in receiving the Sacrament not at all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="reason">
               <head>
                  <hi>REASON</hi> III.</head>
               <p>OTher reasons there be, which I confess I am not able to satisfie: and yet because they are urged more largely by others, I will dispatch them the more cursorily, yet so as to clear them from the manifold exceptions taken against them. In the Preface to the book of Common Prayer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Ceremonies, why some be abrogated, some retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: It is avouched, that none are retained: but such as are apt to stir vp the dull mind of man to the remembrance of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168930:8"/>his duty to God by some notable and special significations, whereby he may be edified: which argueth that the intent of the Church is, to edifie Ministers and People by the use of these retained Ceremonies, and that this edification may be obtained by the aptness of these Ceremonies, both to sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie to us, or to teach and admonish us of some Christian duties, and also to stir up and quicken our dull minds to the performance of the same. Now to retain or use Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies to any such ends, seemeth to me unlawfull in sundry respects.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Because to my understanding, we are forbidden in the second Commandement to make to our selves, or to use any likeness of any thing whereby to draw nearer unto God. Now, if we retain and use these Ceremonies to edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie us, to teach and admonish our selves of some good du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and to stir up, and quicken our dull minds to a mindfull performance of the same, do we not make to our selves cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain likenesses: a likeness of purity, and a likeness of bold profession of Christ crucified, whereby to draw nearer unto God in cloathing our selves with purity, and arming our selves with manfulness in professing of Christ, and fighting under his Banner: when the Apostle saith, <hi>Let all things be done to edification,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.26. I cannot conceive that he giveth us liberty out of our own hearts to devise and to use signes and similitudes of graces and good duties, wherewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to edifie our selves, but yet he chargeth so to dispense the Graces of Gods Spirit in a known Tongue, and so to order the publike duties of Gods worship in the face of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, one man speaking after another, that all things may be done to edification.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Since in Christ we are compleat, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.10. and need not that any man should teach us any duty of Gods worship, or in any otherwise than himself hath provided. Is not this to derogate from Christs prophetical office to devise and use a new manner of teaching and edifying the church by visible signes, and similitudes of graces and good duties, which Christ invented not.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whereas the whole work of edifying the church depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168930:9"/>upon the spirit of God, doth not ordinarily delight to work in any meanes, but such as himself hath san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifiyed to that end. Is not this a tempting of the spirit of God to devise, and use such signes to edify the Church, as either must perish with the use of them, or else put the spirit to shew forth extraordinarily the power of his grace in such meanes, as he is never wont to breath in? Is it not the like tempting of God to put him to shew forth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily the glory of his power or grace, either in refusing to use such meanes as he hath appointed, or in adventuring to use such meanes as he hath not appointed.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To devise and use ceremonies to put us in mind of good duties, and to stirre us up to the remembrance of them is to make to our selves a worshiop of God after the precepts of men, for our Savior Christ seemeth to me to judge of a like practise of the Pharises, for they devised, and used their often washings, to put them in mind of inward cleansing and purifying the heart, and to stirre up themselves to the remmembrance of such duties. And in regard of this it is our Savior saith, <hi>they worshipped him in vaine, teaching and practising such precepts of men,</hi> Mark. 7.1, 2, 3, 4.5, 6, 7.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="reason">
               <head>
                  <hi>REASON</hi> IV.</head>
               <p>NOw to leave the present ill end and use (though from a good heart) aimed at in these ceremonies, and to come to the reason taken from the abuse of them, when the Lord requireth such zeal of his people against superstition, as that they should pollute the Ornaments of their Images and abandon them with detestation out of his worship, <hi>Isa.</hi> 30.22. And when he commendeth <hi>Hezekiah</hi> for breaking in pieces the brazen Serpent unto which the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> burned Incense, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.4. doth he dot call us to pollute the Omaments of the Mass, that is, to translate them to a common use, as Coapes into Quishions, and Surplices into under-Garments, or Napkins, or the like,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168930:9"/>and to abandone them wholly from having any place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the worship of God? And since the crosse hath had the incense of prayer and divine worship offered up unto it, partaking with the brazen serpent in the like sacriledge, why doth it not partake in the like abolishment? Yea, and kneeling in the Sacrament having formerly been an orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yea a religious worship to the breaden God. If we think it meete to reserve it now in honour to the true God, might not <hi>Origen</hi> as well have borne green boughs, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly born to the honour of idols, now to the honour of <hi>Jesus Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it be said the former abuse of a thing cannot take away the lawfull use of it. No idoll-Antichrist or devil can make that unclean to me which Christ by his bloud hath made clean; It is true, there is no former abuse of any ordinance or crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God, or of any profitable invention or workmanship of man that can make them unlawfull for me to use, <hi>Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phinees</hi> notoriously abused the sacrifices of the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, yet (they being ordinances of God) the faithfull restored and continued their lawfull use. The <hi>Corinthian</hi> Idolaters abused much flesh in sacriledges to idols, yet the faithfull <hi>Corinthian</hi> did lawfully eate of the same meate, it being a good creature of God, asking no question for conscience sake, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.25, 26. The Jewes abused their large water-pots to superstitious purifications: yet (they being profitable workmanship of man and fit vessells to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the marriage wine) our Saviour made use of them to the glorifying of God by a miracle, in turning the water in them into wine, and drawing out the same from them (as from cleane vessells) to the serving of the guests <hi>Joh.</hi> 2, 6, 7, 8, 9. upon the same ground we doubtlesse retaine a lawfull use, not only of the Word, and Sacraments, ordinances of God, which yet were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriously abused unto idolatry, and superstition under the Papacy, nor only of the sunne, moone and starres and all the hoast of heaven (creatures of God) which were abused to idolatry and witchcraft by Pagans, but also of Temples and fonts, workmanships of men, they being profitable
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168930:10"/>and expedient vessels for that use they are put to in our congregation. In the old Testament indeed the Israelites were forbidden to reserve the <hi>Canaanitish</hi> temples, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.2, 3. But I conceive that law to be ceremonial, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specting that people only in a double respect, 1 because the <hi>Canaanites</hi> were a people more greivously accursed by God to utter desolation than other nations were, <hi>Dout.</hi> 20 13. to 18.2. Because the reserving of any of their temples would have been a with drawing them from the temple at <hi>Hierusalem,</hi> where God had appointed to put his name there, which reason God himselfe doth not obscurely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.2, 3, 5. In which regard <hi>Josia</hi> also did commendably defile and destroy the temples built both by <hi>Solomon</hi> to idolls, and by <hi>Jeroboam</hi> to the calves, 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 23.13, 14, 15. But now in the dayes of the new Testament, when the blessing of <hi>Abraham</hi> is come upon all nations alike, and no feare is thereby reserving temples abused to idolatry, of withdrawing the people from any set place of his service, he having now appointed none, I doubt not but that notwithstanding the former abuse of popish temples, they being still profitable for the peoples convenient assembling, we may retaine them to a lawfull use.</p>
               <p>But as for these ceremonies, they being neither ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances nor creatures of God, nor any such workmanships of man as are of any profitable expediency in the place which they hold about the worship of God: are they not therefore to be polluted, as the coverings and orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the images, which <hi>Isaiah</hi> speaketh of, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolished, as the brazen serpent, whose profitable use was grown out of date. Thus <hi>Tertullian</hi> that allowed the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and arts invented and abused by the heathen, because a profitable use might be made of them, yet would in no sort allow the wearing of the souldiers garland upon the head, it having been abused. To weare flowers, yea and garlands of flowers in the hand he liketh well of, where both the eye may be refreshed with the beauty of them, and the nostrell with the smell: but to wear the same on the head, where neither the sweetnesse nor the beauty
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168930:10"/>could yeild any refreshing, this he so farre disliketh in a thing abused to idolatry, as that he highly commandeth the souldiers, constant and Christian refusal thereof, though it were to the losse of his own life, and the hazard of many other Christians. If it be demanded who shall judge of the profitable expediency of any workmanship of man, formerly abused to idolatry, seing perhaps men in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority may judge it profitable, which private men may esteem unprofitable: I answer the word and spirit of God, yea, and the light of nature also will easily judge of such a thing. <hi>The spirituall man judgeth all things</hi> saith the Apostle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15. and especially Ministers of the word, to whom is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the discerning of the estate of the flock, and the disp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ensing of a fit portion of spiritual food to their severall state; Are they unable to discerne what places, vestiments, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stures were profitable, and seasonable for their ministration.</p>
               <p>If the antient use of these ceremonies in the dayes of the Fathers of the primitive church be pleaded to mitigate the odiousnesse of their following abuse, and to maintaine the restoring of them to their first good use: I must con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse (to speake under correction of better judgments) though the memory of the worthies of those times be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and honourable, yet could I never discerne the lawfullnesse of the use of these things, since their first in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention; for to begin with the signe of the Crosse, and not to urge the first invention of it by <hi>Valentinus</hi> the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique, and the power ascribed by him to it of purging from sin, as the fanne of Christ, <hi>Jraen. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1.) nor to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plead the necessity and efficacy of the Crosse, which the Fathers ascribing to it, are charitably thought to speake of Christ crucified, but to take the fairest use of the Crosse, at the best hand, when the Christians of those times held forth the sign of the Crosse as a badge of their bold profession of Christ crucified, did they therein performe any acceptable service to God, or his truth? To believe in the heart on the Lord Jesus, and to confesse him with the mouth, as they were called thereunto, even unto the death, and to adorne their confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, with an holy and righteous conversation. In these things
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168930:11"/>stood their comfortable honouring of their Christian profession, but to expresse their honour of Christ cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed by signing themselves with the signe of the Crone, in the presence of infidells, to the provoking of them to the reproach and persecution of Christ, and Christian name; I see no warrant for such unfeasonable over plus devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Gedeon</hi> made an Ephod, and set it up in his Citie <hi>Ophrah</hi> as a trophy of his victory; but was it not to him a ruine, and to his house, yea, and to the people also in tempting them to go an whoring after it? <hi>Jud.</hi> 8.27. The Christians of the primitive Churches made the sign of their Crosse, and held it forth as a glorious trophy of the victory of Christ upon the Crosse: but was it not shortly a ruine to the Church of God in stealing away the hearts of thousands of Christians to go an whoring after it?</p>
               <p>Apparell of Ministers different from other men in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon use no man disliketh, so that therein decency, gravity, simplicity be observed, but the setting of hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed garments (whether surplices or others) apart from common use to the administration of holy pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick duties of Gods worship, though it were accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably prescribed by Pope <hi>Stephen</hi> the first, about the year 260. I dare not justify it as lawfull for the two first reasons above mentioned.</p>
               <p>Kneeling in the Sacrament I read not either practised, or prescribed in the Church till the dayes of <hi>Honorius</hi> the third, when as Transubstantiation for the name, had been formerly hatched by <hi>Jnnocent</hi> the third, and (for the thing by <hi>Leo</hi> the ninth) so that if we carry our selves not as servants, but as children to the fathers (as they are called) of the primitive Church; If we imbrace and imitate their sayings, and doings not with servile neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity, but with Christian liberty (as children parents in the Lord) as we cannot discerne any just ground of their first inventing and practising of these things, neither shall we ever be able to restore them to their first good use, which indeed they never had. But say their first use had been good and behoveful to the Church of God
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168930:11"/>was it not so likewise, yea, and much more with the brazen serpent? Had it not his first institution from the authority of God our heavenly Father, and his first use to the healing of the venemous stingings of the fiery ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent? Yea, and to the lifting up of the hearts of the faithfull to the faithfull beholding of Christ lifted up up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Crosse, and yet since it being afterwards idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trously abused, was abolished, why fareth it not alike with these ceremonies, whose first institution was not so authentical, nor their use so behoveful, nor their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing abuse lesse abhominable? if it be said <hi>Hezekiah</hi> did well in breaking the brazen serpent, to abolish the abuse thereof with the thing it self: but yet that he had not done amisse, if he had only removed the abuse, and reserved the thing; the truth is, it was the expresse com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of God that things idolatrously abused (even in lesse grosse manner than it was) should not be clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed but polluted, nor the abuse removed but the thing, <hi>Isai.</hi> 30.22. and therefore to say (as some do further) that <hi>Hezekiah</hi> therefore removed the brazen serpent, because the abuse of it was desperate, and past hope of restoring to his innocent use; and therefore ours to be better borne with, whose abuse is more recoverable. Is not this to say, he would have broken the expresse Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, which requireth the removall of things lesse abused, whethersoever the abuse be desperate or not? Yea, is not this to say things at random (as men do which would faine say somewhat, when they know not what to say) to say the abuse was desperate when the Scripture saith no such matter, how can any man tell the abuse was desperate when the Scripture is silent herein; or shall we think <hi>Hezekiah</hi> would not have removed it, if the abuse were dangerous, unlesse withall it had been desperat? It is no sufficient ground to conceive the abuse of the brazen serpent, which <hi>Hezekiah</hi> abolished, was desperate, because otherwise he would have aswell destroyed <hi>Solomons</hi> idolatrous temples, and the images therein, whose abuse was then neglected; for (under cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168930:12"/>I do not think that <hi>Hezekiah</hi> spared to destroy those temples and images, though we afterwards read that <hi>Josia</hi> destroyed them in his time, 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 23.13, 14. for is it not said that <hi>Hezekiah</hi> did that which was right in the sight of the Lord, according to all that his father <hi>David</hi> had done, that he took away the high places (that is) the idolatrous temples, and that he brake the images, 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 18.3, 4. Now that <hi>Josiah</hi> came afterward to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy them, it was not because <hi>Hezekiah</hi> had neglected them, but because <hi>Manasseh</hi> reigning between them both, had repayred and built again those idolatrous temples and images which <hi>Hezekiah</hi> his father had broken down, 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 21.3. 2 <hi>Cro.</hi> 33.3, 19. To say <hi>Hezekiah</hi> removed the serpent, <hi>flagrante delicto,</hi> the idolatrous abuse of it being then in the heate: though this might be some excusall of our Governors forbearance of these ceremonies in these dayes, (wherein the abuse of them is allayed) yet is not this to confesse an oversight in those worthy restorers of religion in the dayes of our Fathers, who bore with them, even then when their abuse was as gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and grosse and busy as ever? And what though the like abuse of these things doth not continue in like mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure in our reformed Churches. Is it nothing to us how notoriously these things are abused in popish Churches? when our neighbours houses are on a light fire round about us, is it nothing to us to let such light fuell (as we have no use for) ly still in our houses, so easily apt to take hold on the same fire, wherewith they are consumed? To say the brazen serpent was more grossely abused than any of our ceremonies have been, is not this rather to cast lotts what to speak, then to weigh what to speak? is offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of incense to the brazen serpent an abuse of a more proper, and essentiall sacrifice due to God than the offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of prayer for salvation to the signe of the Crosse? Is not prayer coupled with incense as, at least, an equall worship. <hi>Psal.</hi> 14.2. yea, is not prayer the substance of that worship, whereof incense is but the shadowe? Is not prayer both inward and outward worship, and incense
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:168930:12"/>but outward only. Finally to say that the brazen serpent, which <hi>Hezekiah</hi> abolished was the same in number which was abused, whereas our ceremonies are not the same in number, but in kind only, doth not justify our preserving of them from abolishment: for first, as they be not the same in number, which the Papists abused: so neither are they the same in number which the Fathers used before the Papacy, if they be the same which the Fathers used, as is alledged to authorize them, why are they not the same also, which the Papists abused to abolish them? Again when God chargeth his people to abolish the names of strange Gods out of their places, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.3. when he promiseth to take away their names, and remembrances out of the mouthes of his people, <hi>Hos.</hi> 2.17. doth he not call for the abolishment of all idols which have been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly abused? not onely the same in number, but even all of the same kind, or name, whose mention might renew any honourable memorial of the former? We do indeed call the names of some moneths in the year, and of all the dayes in the week after the names of the Planets, and other heathenesh Gods, which, though it was of old condemned by some antient divines, when the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of the heathenish Gods was fresh amongst the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, yet now that their memory is worne out of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples mindes, we do not sticke at the use of their names, for the distinction of dayes and times no more than <hi>Luke</hi> did in describing the ship wherein <hi>Paul</hi> sailed by the name of the heathen Gods, <hi>Castor</hi> and <hi>Pollux, Acts</hi> 28.11. but what maketh this the retaining of the names of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Gods for distinction sake, to the retaining both of the names and the things themselves, which have been idolatrously abused, not for distinction sake, but for honours sake: besides when God forbiddeth the <hi>Israelites</hi> to do after the manner of the heathen, <hi>Lev.</hi> 18.3. he doth not only debarre us from retaining the same things in number, which they abused, but even the same in kind, and proportion, neither doth he speak of things simply evil in their own nature, but of such also as of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168930:13"/>themselves might have been used indifferently. They are forbidden to cut round the corners of their head. <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.27. and to make any baldnesse between their eyes. <hi>Deut.</hi> 14.1. both which, though the <hi>Gentile</hi> used sinfully, as a signe of immoderate mourning for the dead; yet the things of themselves, of their oun nature, were indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, and might have been used either for decency, or for signes of deep, though not immoderate mourning for the dead, which yet God allowed not to his people. As there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was not lawfull for the <hi>Israelites</hi> to use such like Ceremonies for indifferent, which the <hi>Gentiles</hi> sinfully had abused; so neither may we use such like ceremonies which the Papists sinfully have abused for indifferent: and when the Lord sorbiddeth his people to worship him as the <hi>Gentiles</hi> worshipped their Gods, or to do so unto him as they did unto theirs, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.30, 31. doth he not likewise forbid us to kneele to him in receiving the Sacrament, as the Papists <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n receiving the Sacrament, do kneel unto their breaden God. They therefore that (out of their learning) tell us that our ceremonies are not the same in forme and substance) that the Popish ceremonies be, because the superstitious intent, and use whereunto they apply theirs is wanting in ours. They do not consider that the Lord forbiddeth his people, not only to use the same ceremonies, which the <hi>Gentiles</hi> used to the same end, which they intended, but also to use them in any religious service at all, yea, or in any civil office, like unto them, where the use leaveth no profit behind it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="reason">
               <head>
                  <hi>REASON</hi> V.</head>
               <p>I Am now to come to the last Reason (which yet is not of the least weight) taken from the offence, which is given by the using of these ceremonies; offence I call that, whereby the conscience of a weak brother is edifyed to sin, (as the Apostle speaketh, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.10.) whether it be by emboldning him to do evil, or by discouraging, and hind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ering of him from doing that which is good, offence
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:168930:13"/>may be given, either by doing some good duty behove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to be done, or by doing some thing before others, either evil in it self, or appearing to be evil; or else by using our liberty in things lawfull (or as they call them indiffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent) but yet in expedient. The offence that is given by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any good duty behovefull to be done is no sin unto him that giveth it; for thus our Saviour offended the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rises by teaching an wholesome, necessary truth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.12. whose offence in this case he regarded not, <hi>ver.</hi> 14. The offence that is given by doing that which is evil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore others, is alwayes a double evil, both in regard of the sinne in it self, and also of the mischeife that it doth to others, whether it be that the evil be done by practising some few sinnes to the evil example of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p>Or by speech, or gesture, perswading, counsailing, commanding, countenancing sin, or discouraging, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering another in any good duty, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.28. 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 22.28, 29, 30. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.22, 23. or by forbearing to punish sin in our place, according to the due desert of it, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.13. or finally by defiling any ordinance of God, or any good duty to the provoking of others, to the abstayning, and abhorring, not, from the abuse only, but from the duty or ordinance it selfe, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.17, 24. The offence that is given by doing something that hath in it appearance of evil, is an evil also, 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 3.22. which <hi>Eleazer</hi> worthily avoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, 2 <hi>Machab.</hi> 6.21, 22, 23, 24, 25. The offence that is given by using our liberty in things lawfull, but yet inexpedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent (of which we read, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.23. the Apostle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth as evil, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.20, 21. for instance, to eate of meat sacrificed to idols is in it self lawfull (or as they call it indifferent) because every creature of God is good (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.4.) and <hi>to the pure all things are pure,</hi> Tit. 1.15. and we know that an idoll is nothing in the world (and therefore hath no power to pollute that unto us, the profitable use whereof Christ hath sanctified by his blood to us) 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.4. but yet to eate of such things, when others thereby would be edifyed to sin, when as they by thine example would be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:168930:14"/>emboldned to eate of such meates, not as thou doest, as of meates pure, and not hurt by the idols, but according to their own weaknesse, as of meats sacrificed to the idol, and sanctifyed by it, this would be a greivous sin in thee against thy brother, for he having conscience of the idol, that is in conscience bearing reverence to the idol, and see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee eate of such meates as were sacrificed to the idol, to wit, to the service and honour of the idol, he verily think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thou honourest, and servest the idol, and so is em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldned himself likewise to eate of such things to the honour and service of the idol, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.7, to 12. In which regard the Apostle professeth he would never eate flesh while he lived, than thus to offend his brother, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.13. yea, and commandeth all Christians to abstain from use of their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in this case, 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 10.28. yea, further such tender regard he hath and would have us to have to the inward peace and comfort of our bretheren, that he teacheth it to be a part of our charitable walking to abstaine from such things (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise lawfull) as whereby our brother would be greived for that we do, and happily think the worse of us for so doing, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.15. Now then to apply these things to our present purpose, say that these ceremonies enjoyned, in themselves might be lawfully used (which yet in the service of God we have allready shewed they may not) neverthelesse since here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we should give manifold offence to the consciences of our bretheren, were there no other reason but this, yet even in this very respect, were we bound to abstaine from the use of them, for first, is it a light offence which we offer to the Magistrates, whose souls ought to be most pretious in our sight) when we by yielding to the practise of such ceremonies do build up them in this erroneous opinion (not only that such ceremonies are indifferent, but also that it is lawfull for them to enjoyne and urge upon the Church of God the use of humane ordinances, in the service of God, which perish with the use of them? againe, shall we not offend the separatists, by admitting such ceremonies into the Church (as through their weaknesse) thrust them out of the Church: shall we not offend others of our bretheren, who though otherwise
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:168930:14"/>they hold communion with our Churches, yet will by no means communicate with us at such times, where they see these ceremonies used by us? were it not much safer, (for their sakes and the separatists) by admitting our brethren into the Church to thrust out the ceremonies, than by admitting the ceremonies to thrust out our brethren? What shall we say many ignorant people, whereof too many are found in every congregation? shall we not offend them by using the Surplice, when they thinke the prayers not well hollowed without it? the Crosse, when they think the child not to have (as they call it) his full Christendome without it. Kneeling in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, when some of them are the more emboldned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to worship their maker in the elements, and other think the Sacrament unworthily and unreverently received without it. They who think such ignorant people are not to be found in all <hi>England,</hi> are themselves as yet scarce well acquainted with their own congregations. The Church-Papists amongst us (especially such of them as of ignorance, and weakenesse are devoted that way) they also are to be rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned of us, as weak brethren, as the weake idolatrous <hi>Gentiles</hi> were of <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.7, 10, 11. and shall we not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them by holding forth the Surplice which he reverenceth as an hallowed vestment, the Crosse which he religiously adoreth, kneeling in Sacrament, whereby he (taking the opportunity) worshippeth devoutly his breaden God: final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when we see so many both silenced Ministers, and other Christians strongly possessed with opinion of the unlawfullnes of these ceremonies, shall we not at all offend them? or at least greive them by holding up these things as the matter of our liberty, which have held them under as the matter of their misery. The reply here made is cheifly this, that all this burthen of giving offence, doth lie more heavy upon them who refuse the ceremonies, than upon them who yeild unto the use of them, for if we refuse the ceremonies, do we not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Christian Magistrates by provoking them to think of us, as disobedient, and factious, and foolishly precise, streyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the gnat of a ceremony, and swallowing the camel of disloyalty, and turbulency? do we not offend the whole body
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:168930:15"/>of the people provoking them to the like disorderly contempt of lawfull autholity?</p>
               <p>For answer hereunto, first this doth fully satisfie me, that the burthen of giving offence can neverly upon them who do in their conscience judge these ceremonies not to be indiffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, but to be unlawful in the service of God: for if we do not see our liberty in the lawful use of them, how should we be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for not using that liberty, which to our understanding God hath not allowed us? they who esteem these things as indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, and see their liberty in conscience to use them, or use them not, they cannot excuse themselves from sin, if they use them unseasonably, to the offence of others, because they with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out scruple of conscience might as freely have omitted them, as now use them uncharitably: but such as have faithfully en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to search out the bounds of their liberty in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, and yet cannot see their liberty of using these things, without sin they are exempted from danger of offending of any, by forbearing that liberty which they cannot use with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out sin, for we may not commit any sin to avoyd offence, so that whatsoever offence falleth out upon occasion of these ceremonies, either from the use or the refusall of them, cannot be imputed unto them, who would gladly do to the utmost what lawfully they might to prevent offence, but unto them only, who knowing their liberty in these things, as well to forbear them as to use them, do yet not withstanding use them, to the occasioning of all those many offences which are taken of them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, as for such who think these ceremonies other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise indifferent, but yet (as things now stand) inexpedient, and unlawfull only in regard of offence, I think they take the safer course to prevent offence rather by refusing then by usinge of them, for when it is pretended that by using these things we onely offend a few private persons, whereas by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusing them we offend publick magistrates, it cannot indeed be denyed, but that the offence given to a publick person is more dangerous (if other things be equal) than that which is given to a private (because a publick person stumbling at any offence draweth many others to fall after him, and by offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:168930:15"/>him we sin against loyalty and charity both, whereas by of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending a private person we sin against charity only) yet I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not see in this case how the magistrate may truly be sayed to be offended, when judging these things to be indifferent, may safely remove them and the offence with them, when it pleaseth him. If there be such weakness in a magistrate, as to take offence at any mans forbearance of these things, there is in him also no lesse strength (even strength of authority) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by by taking these things out of the way, or rather letting them fall of themselves, he may prevent the occasion of his own offence, and the offence of others. The case standeth not so with private persons: if they be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the use of these things, though their persons be lighter then the Magistrates, yet their offence is heavier, as being remedilesse. Besides though the offence of publick persons were every way heaviest, yet for any man to use his liberty in these things against his conscience were to offend against God, who being the most publick, and Soveraign Governour above all, the offence against him were heaviest of all. There is no fear that Ministers by forbearance of these things shal offend the people by provoking them to like disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly contempt of lawfull authority, for it is no contempt (no nor shew of contempt) when a Minister, either in conscience of his duty to God, or in charity toward his weake brethren shall forbeare the use of some things commanded, as indiffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent by the Magistrate, and in the meane time shall quietly and reverently submit himself, his body, his goods, his life, yea, and which is more (the very life of his life, his ministry to the discretion and pleasure of the Magistrate. Is there any colour of disloyalty or turbulency in this or any semblance of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly contempt of lawfull authority? Nay rather is there not herein an evident building up of the people, to a reasonable Christian and conscionable obedience of the Magistrate, when we rather quietly submit our selves to the losse of our dearest comforts, than blindfold yeild to obey his ecclesiastical lawes, till we see them grounded on reasons from the word, which may assure our consciences that they are commanded in the Lord. For a Minister to obey the ecclesiasticall lawes of a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:168930:16"/>Magistrate, without looking for warrant of them from the word; is not to build up the people to a Christian and reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble obedience of the Magistrates, but to a blind and carnall obedience of him.</p>
               <p>Do we not offend the separatist in laying such grounds of non-conformity, whereupon they build their separation? The separatists too have built their separation upon the grounds of non-conformity, is as likely as was the raising of <hi>Goodwin</hi> sands upon <hi>Tenterton</hi> steeple, though not conforming to ceremonies argueth them unlawfull, or at least inexpedient, and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the Church to be blemished, that is encombered with them, yet doth it therfore argue the Church to be no Church, or the worship of God in it no worship? Sooner may bloud be wrunge and prest out of milke, than such a schisme out of the Sincere milke of such wholsome doctrine, what hath stirred up their separation themselves tell us plainly in their writings, they feeling the smart of their own pain, can best tell us where their pain lieth.</p>
               <p>Do we not offend the ignorant people, especially our weake followers in nuzeling them up in a nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive superstition (as it is called) weare not, crosse not, kneele not.</p>
               <p>Do we not offend the Papists by casting out the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ceremonies of the Church, the more to alienate them from our new-fanglednesse? and as for the silenced Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, and such other Christians addicted to them, what need we regard the offence of them, since they of all others are not weake bretheren, but the strongest of all either indeed, or at least in their own conceit.</p>
               <p>And what ground is there (I pray you) of nuzeling up the ignorant people in a negative superstition, by not Crossing, not wearing, not kneeling, as is appointed by man, not by God if superstition be <hi>supra statutum,</hi> the doing of this or that beyond, what is comanded us by Gods statutes, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the twaine (thinke ye) carrieth the Superstition, to use and urge Crossing, wearing, kneeling, which are all of them beyond what God hath commanded, or not to use crossing, wearing, kneeling, because God hath not comanded them? Is
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:168930:16"/>it not farre more truly called a deniall or negation of supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then a negative superstition to deny those things which are <hi>Supra statutum,</hi> beyond the statutes of God. The Papists, if through love of antiquity they have been offended, and aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from our religion, by our new-fangledness in casting out the ancient ceremonies of the Church, methinketh they might the sooner be wonne to our religion by seeing our whole service restored to the antient primitve simplicity of the first institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, was not the service of God in the Apostles times freely and fully administred? the Minister being addressed without the Surplice, baptisme without the Crosse, the Lords supper without kneeling? kneeling, Crosse, Surplice are novelities to the antient first institution, yea and practise also of those dayes, yea and many dayes after.</p>
               <p>Finally the silenced Ministers, and such other Christians as cleave unto them in opinion, and affection, though none of them were weake bretheren but all strong, yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the offence of them to be excused, <hi>Barnabas</hi> was a stronge man in Christ, as being full of the holy Ghost, and faith, <hi>Act,</hi> 1.24. yet <hi>Peter</hi> was not therefore excusable for giving offence unto him, when by his example he drew him to like dissimulation, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.13. Christ himself was so strong, as that no weaknesse was found in him, and yet <hi>Peter</hi> was sharply reproved for giving offence even to him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.23. So that were all the silenced Ministers, and their adherents never so strong, yea, and never so strongly possessed of the unlawfullnes of these ceremonies, yet by our conformity in yeilding to them, may they also be brought to like dissimulation, and to favour themselves (as <hi>Peter</hi> counselled our Saviour) in preventing their suffering for these things. But furthermore if we account all these Ministers and such others to be strong men, why do we not respect, and followe their judgement, and practise in the forbearance of these things? If we account them weake, why do we not forbeare these things to prevent the offending of them, as of weake brethren. Besides the trueth is, though some of them be grown so strong in wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and brotherly love, that they are able (by the grace of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:168930:17"/>Christ to passe by an offence) and so Christ be preached in any sort to rejoyce therein, and neither be drawn themselves to assemble with their own consciences by sight of others conformitancy nor be induced to thinke the worse of others who (otherwise walking conscionably) do use their liberty in these things: yet verily sundry others there be, even amongst them, which cannot so easily moderate their judgements, and affection, and speeches towards such as they see follow the course of the times, in yeilding to these things, yea, and all of them the more strong, and heavenly minded they be, the less can they chuse but greive to see any fearing God, defiling themselves with these empty ruciments, which themselves are perswaded to be unlawfull: wherefore since by the use of these ceremonies we shall give offence to so many of our bretheren, so many sundry vayes, doth not brotherly love constrain us rather to forbear these things, though with hazard of our own outward peace, and the peace of our Ministry, than to use them to the prejudice of the inward peace of our own consciences, and the consciences of others. If it be said, It is writen woe be unto every Minister, if he preach not the Gospell, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16. but it is no where written, woe be unto him if he weare a Surplice, or use the Crosse, or stoop to kneeling in receiving the Sacrament. The answer is ready, it is also written, woe be to the world because of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, it cannot be but that offences shall come, but woe be to him by whom the offence commeth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.7. If it be said, that the offence that cometh by these things is not given but taken, or if it be given, it is only by accident, by reason of the weaknesse of such as take it, though it were true (which yet is not) considering what hath been said touching the sinfullness of these things in themselves in the service of God, and their aptnes to hurt others, yet that will not free us from the burthen of that woe pronounced against such by whom offence commeth, for the Scripture maketh no difference between giving offence and doing any thing by which offence cometh, though it be by accident. The offence which <hi>Paul</hi> so much insisteth in, of eating things sacrificed to idolls, is not in it self an offence given (for in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:168930:17"/>it self it is lawfull and good) but taken only, or if given, given only by accident by reason of the weaknesse of some brother, who hitherto hath conscience of the idolI, and seeing a man of knowledge, eats of things sacrificed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the idoll is imboldened to continue still in his idolatry, doing sacrifice, and service to the idoll, and therefore which way soever an offence cometh, by giving, or taking, by it self or by accident, wo be to him by whom it cometh: onely he which is exempted from this woe in case of offence, is such an one by whom offence cometh either by doing some necessary duty of his calling (as Christ offended the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rises</hi> by preaching the seasonably wholsome doctrine of what things defile a man, and yet was guiltlesse, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.10, 11, 12, 14.) or else by using Christian liberty to the offence only of false bretheren, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.4, 5. If it be said againe, the offence which now is given by such as use these ceremonies is therfore guiltlesse) because it being now called into question vvhether these things of indifferency may be appointed, and used in the service of God, or no, and they know it to be a truth of God concerning Christian liberty, that it is lawfull so to do, they shall seeme to forsake the maintenance of this truth, if they shall now forbeare the practise of it (in which case <hi>praestat nasci scandalum, quam deseri verum</hi>) The answer is plain, though it were a truth, that it were lawfull to appoint matters of indifferency in Gods service, and that these things were but matters of indifferency, yet is it not safe unseasonably to maintain this truth by practising the liberty thereof to the offence of the weak; Was there not a truth of God concerning Christian liberty called in question in <hi>Pauls</hi> time: whether it were lawfull to eat of things sacrificed to Idols, or no: and did he for maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of this truth use his liberty in eating thereof? no verily, he professeth he will rather never eat flesh while the world standeth, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.13. Was there not a like truth called in question, when one believed he might eat all things, another which was weak did eat hearbs: one esteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed every day alike, another esteemed one day above ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.2, 5. And, did <hi>Paul</hi> advise them that had faith
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:168930:18"/>to see their liberty in these things, publikely to profess and maintain this faith, by using their liberty to the offence of the weak: nay rather, saith he, <hi>It is good neither to eat flesh, nor to drink wine, nor any thing whereby thy brother stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth, or is offended, or made weak; hast thou faith, have it with thy self before God, blessed is he that condemneth not himself in that which he alloweth,</hi> Rom. 14.21, 22. Indeed it is true, if fundamental points of Doctrine concerning things necessary to salvation be called into question: as, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Christ be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or the like, there it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite to contend earnestly for the faith once given to the Saints, whosoever be offended, and in this case it is true <hi>(praestat nasci scandalum quam deseri verum)</hi> better offence be given than the least jot of Gods necessary truth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saken. But in such truths, in which ignorance, or errour, is no prejudice to salvation on either side, as in this case, of the lawfull or unlawfull use of these Ceremonies in Gods service, <hi>praestat sileri verum, quam nasci scandalum,</hi> bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the truth be left untaught, at least unpractised for a time, than offence given to weak brethren.</p>
               <p>Two Remedies yet remain behind, whereby it is thought all danger of offence may be safely and sufficiently prevented, the one by teaching of the Minister, the other by the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Magistrate; if there were, say they, any such danger of offence, it may easily be helped by the wise in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of a faithfull Minister, declaring the lawfull use of these things: which, since it hath not been wanting these many yeares, both in word and writing, no man can now pretend ignorance or weakness, so, that now if any be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, it is not so much out of tenderness of conscience, as out of wilfulness of humour, which is not to be so much cherished, as for it to forbear our lawfull-liberty in things indifferent, whereunto I will not answer (as many do upon too good ground) that many Congregations have been long without a teaching-Minister, (and what instruction have they had) and others without a faithfull Minister (and how re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardless have they been by any wise instruction to prevent offence?) But this I demand, what instructions are they
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:168930:18"/>which a Minister can give in this case to prevent offence, though he set himself as wisely and faithfully (as he may) to perform it? Shall he teach that it is lawfull for Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stical Magistrates to ordain strict penal Lawes touching mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of indifferency, that it is lawfull to command such cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances, or manner of administration of Gods worship, as God himself in his word hath not commanded; That it is lawfull to appoint and use edifying Ceremonies to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct and stir up the dull heart of man to some duties of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion: that it is lawfull to retain Popish unprofitable Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies wherewith they have abominably dishonored God, with them to honour God and his service; that it is lawfull for a Christian Magistrate, not to regard offence in giving his Commandments touching things of this kind for his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment taketh away scandal in things indifferent. But, are not all these so many points of false Doctrine (as hath been formerly shewed, and shall we teach falshoods to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent offence: but say it were possible to find out such true and wholsome doctrine to teach the people as might be fit to prevent offence in these things; offence may still con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue notwithstanding this: for, though a Minister should give never such just grounds of satisfaction, yet it oft com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to pass that a weak conscience resteth not satisfied; it is God only that can satisfie the doubting conscience, when thou happily seest the clear evidence of thine own reasons, it may be, he, what through weakness of judgement, what through want of illumination, what through tenderness of conscience seeth it not, and what shall a Minister do in this case? shall he now boldly use his liberty in these things which he hath taught to be free, shall he wash his hands, and say, I am innocent from the blood of these men that are still offended after so much instruction, if they now perish, their blood be upon their own heads, let them perish: Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le <hi>Paul</hi> was of a far other mind, when he professed, he would rather never eat flesh while the world standeth, than offend his brother, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.13. It is not to be thought but in all that time <hi>Paul</hi> would take occasion to instruct, and seek to satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie a weak brother; but yet, suppose he should continue in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:168930:19"/>his weakness unsatisfied, <hi>Paul</hi> also would continue in his wise and charitable forbearance of the use of his liberty, while the world standeth: do not say therefore, how long shall I continue teaching my weak brother, till seven times, I say not till seven times, but till seventy times seven, even so long as he continueth a weak brother: if the question be how long such an one may be counted a weak brother, the answer is, so long, as being weak in knowledge he discern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not the light of that satisfaction shewed unto him, or being weak in affection is still apt to be grieved at the use of thy liberty, and the weakness of such an one is the more to be tendered, if it be joyned with a desire to learn the truth, and care to do according to measure of knowledge received, humbly using the meanes to build up himself: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed if such an one, though he were not yet satisfied in the lawfull use of this, or that, yet would assure thee, that thy practice contrary to his judgement should not offend nor grieve him, but he would wish thee to use thy liberty, and both would rest in not judging one another, then wert thou free to use thy liberty in matters truly of indifferency. For such a brother, though he may be still weak in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, yet is grown strong in Christian affection: but if the question further be, whether a man after so long instruction without receiving satisfaction, doth not now degenerate from a weak brother to a false brother, whose offence is not to be regarded; for, <hi>Paul</hi> that did circumcise <hi>Timothy</hi> for the weak brother, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.3. would not circumcise <hi>Titus</hi> for all the false brethren, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.3, 4, 5. I answer, A false brother may easily be discerned from a weak brother by two marks: 1. A false brother creepeth into the fellowship of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to spy out the liberty which they have in Christ, to bring them into the bondage of observance of such things, which themselves for their own practice make no reckoning of, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.4. compared with <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.12, 13. 2. A false brother is wedded to his own opinion and practice, not so much out of weakness of judgement, as out of strength of will with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out seeking after knowledge, or desire to receive instruction offered; as it is with many Papists in observing their Fish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:168930:19"/>and such other traditions. These will either not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with you at all, or if they do, will resolve to hold fast their own conclusion, and when you shew them their errour, will either seek to divert you to a new question, or with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger fret at the light you offer them, or bring you back again the same reasons to the same issue, with wearisome repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: It is a signe a man seeketh not truth but victory in a suit of Law, when seeing the issue of his Plea fall out clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly against him, non-suiteth himself to bring it about again: so is it here a signe, not of a weak brother desirous of truth, but of a false brother carried with sinister purposes: when he, beginning to see the error of his cause, starteth aside, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to a new cause, or to the fetching of the same doubts about again; it is not so with weak bretheren, they would be loath to bind others, where they do not see them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves bound first, and when you shall reveal any light to them for their satisfaction, they gladly embrace it, if they be not able to discern it, they stand not contending with you, but rather desire your prayers that God would perswade their hearts of these things whereof they are not able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince themselves.</p>
               <p>I come now to that other help to prevent offence, which some think sufficient thereunto: to wit, the authority of the Magistrate; for, they who teach that the authority of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate taketh away scandal in matters of indifferency, they know not (as they say) what offence any man can give by the use of these things, since the authority of the Magistrate hath peremptorily required the performance of them, for, things otherwise indifferent do in some sort alter their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, when they are commanded by lawfull Authority, and may not then be omitted contrary to Law. So that now, the performance of these things being in some sort a necessary duty, we may not omit them for avoyding of offence. But this whole device containeth in it a double error: 1. That the authority of the Magistrate maketh that, which before was a matter of indifferency, to become a duty of necessity, which if it were true, I do not see but by the same autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, a Magistrate might make that which before was a duty
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:168930:20"/>of necessity to become a matter of indifferency; it is an act of the same power to bind unto sin, and to release from sin. Again, if it were so, that the authority of the Magistrate did make a matter of indifferency to become a duty of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity, then surely the breach of any of his Commandments (though in a matter otherwise of indifferency) would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a sin unto us to be eschewed upon pain of damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And, what were this else than to put into the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates hand power to kill the soul, as well as the body; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that speech of our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.28. Yea, as the Magistrate is Gods Minister to kill the bodies of such as disobey God in hainous crimes: so God should be his Minister to kill the souls of such as disobey the Magistrate in things indifferent. How much more safe, and sound Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine were it, to reserve unto God the Prerogative that he may first command a thing, and then see it to be good, and to leave unto the Magistrate this direction: That he is first to see a thing to be good, and then command is. Secondly, The other error which that device containeth in it, is, that the authority of the Magistrate taketh away scandal in matters of indifferency; for, is not this to make the Commandment of God of none effect by the authority of man? If God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand thou shalt not give offence, by using thy liberty un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seasonably in matters of indifferency: and we say, by the gift of obedience, which thou offerest to the Magistrate, thou shalt be free; Is not this to obey man, to the disobedience of God? The Magistrate himself is a Christian man, and therefore himself bound by the Law of Christian love, not to give offence to any of his weak bretheren, much less to command others to do that which is offensive. Further, offence given is a soul-murther, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. A Magistrate can no more lawfully make an offence given to a weak brother no offence, than the murther of an innocent no murther.</p>
               <p>Finally, Since the very Law of God touching matter of Ceremony ceaseth to bind, when the observance thereof would prove prejudicial to the welfare of mans body, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.3, 4. Shall not much more the law of man touching mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of indifferency cease also to bind, when the observance
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:168930:20"/>thereof would procure scandal, and scandal perishing to the soul of man. It is not therefore in matters of indifferency the law of man that taketh away scandal, but scandal rather, that taketh away the law of man.</p>
               <p>These are the things, Reverend Sir, which entring into my mind upon occasion of such meditations in reading of the Scriptures, have detained me from seeing any lawfull liberty to yield unto this required conformity; God is my record, whom I desire to serve in the liberty of the Spirit of his Son; if I were able to satisfie my self in resolving these Reasons, I would neither be troublesome to your self, nor other my friends, in seeking your help to perform it for me: neither durst I hazard the liberty of my poor ministery, but upon that evidence of the truth, whereupon I would think my self bound (if I were called thereto) to hazard also my life. If God have revealed any further light to you touching these things, then as yet I can see (as I know by reason of the ripeness of the yeares, the soundness of your judgement, the great variety of the reading, it well may be) I pray you for the antient undeserved love to me, for your love to Gods Church, for your love to Christian liberty, impart it plainly, and liberally to me. I trust the Lord who fashioneth all our hearts, and all our opinions (will of his mercy) keep me from shutting mine eyes against any light of his truth, which himself by you or others shal reveal to me. The Lord guide and keep our hearts in the wayes of his truth, and peace in Christ Jesus, </p>
               <closer>Amen. Amen.</closer>
               <closer>Tibi soli Domine Jesu.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="objections_anticipated_and_addressed">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:168930:21"/>
            <head>Satans bulwark for conformity.</head>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>PRide in opposing and preferring private judgement, against</hi> tot, tantos, tales.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> I would be loath to subcribe unto <hi>Calvin</hi>'s insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution and yet prefer not my judgements to his.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Pride would rather provoke to yeild to authority to crosse, and crush the malignant oppositions, and expectations of all adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries, which were as easily done (if there were no other let, as to draw a crosse line.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Singularity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> It is incident to a good cause <hi>Jer.</hi> 15.10.</p>
            <list>
               <item>2. <hi>The number of the others not so great which out of setled judgement think them expedient.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>The Convocation-house consists but of a number of divines, each diocesse (whereof each containeth many shires, send but</hi> 2 <hi>Clerkes; not so many as the</hi> 300. <hi>silenced.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Of such as yeild, some doe it not simply approv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the things, but in case of deprivation.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Let the King be pleased to ordaine the abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, of these things, and subsription to the superstition and offensivenesse of these things, and see if</hi> 300 <hi>will refuse it even to deprivation.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Authoritly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> It is allwayes to be obeyed either in.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>Doing.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>Suffering, yet in all antiquity no president for punishing so severely the neglect of matters of indifferency.</hi> Victo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <hi>rash excommunication exploded by</hi> Jrenaeus.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:168930:21"/>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Godly authority occupied about matters of greater impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance may slip in circumstancial matters,</hi> 2 Sam. 6.1, 2, 3. <hi>with</hi> 1 Cron. 15.12, 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>No outward thing defileth a man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>True, there is a lawfull use of all things, but not in Gods worship, and other cases, as of love-feasts, but not in the Lord Supper: Womens apparell lawfull but not on a mans backe. Is not here also something indifferent, yet in case becomeing abhomination, <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.5. as making men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable.</p>
            <p>I will not be brought under the power of any thing, which he is said to be, that either cannot be without a thing, or will not or cannot be at all with it.</p>
            <p>The latter branch not true, for then our abandoning sin, were to be brought under the power of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Indifferency of the things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> 1. That is denied of such as suffer in regard of
<list>
                  <item>1. Churches intent to stire up.</item>
                  <item>2. Addition to the manner of worship beyond the word.</item>
                  <item>3. Former and present abuse.</item>
                  <item>4, Scandall.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Though indifferency were granted, yet they ought not to be commanded, as being beyond the Apostles commission,</hi> Mat. 28.20. Col. 2.20, 21, 22.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Ʋniformity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> The wo d provideth not for it but for unity, which is best procured either
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>By removing such a partition wall, Eph.</hi> 2.14, 15.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>By forbidding, judging and despising of either party,</hi> Rom. 14.3.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The place of <hi>Col.</hi> 2.20, 21, 22. though spoken against ceremonies, wherein will-worship was put, yet stre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cheth to all human inven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pauls</hi> intent in the Epistle to the <hi>Galathians</hi> is to reason
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:168930:22"/>against the necessity of the ceremoniall law, but his grounds stretch also to refute popish justification by the morall law.</p>
            <p>In doubtfull casesas, this about <hi>Hierarchy</hi> and ceremonies, who in the right known by these signes:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>What Spirit resteth upon the sufferers, if that of glory, then they suffer for righteousnesse sake,</hi> 1 Pet. 4.14.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>What do they seeke, if not their own bellies but Gods glory with neglect of their bellies, then it is not they that make the Schisme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rom. 16.17, 18.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="query_anticipated_and_answered">
            <p>BEloved brother in or blesed Saviour. I desire your o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion concerning the nature of a religious ceremonie, what you conceive to be the main difference between a cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ony religious and civil, whether it stand not in this, one is used in acts of divine worship, the other in civil. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of my doubt, and question is because of the altar set up by the 12 tribes, <hi>Josh.</hi> 22. which was for a religious end, but yet I know not whether to be counted religious, as rather only civil, as beeing a witnesse of communion between them and their brethren, which is but a civil thing, though the end be holy and religious: If religious ceremonies have place on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in or about acts of Gods worship, then this was no religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ceremony, as never being used in any such act. On the other side I desire allso to know what you thinke of the <hi>Jews</hi> philacteries, and fringes, which were both commanded of God, and to a religious end, whether you would call them religious ceremonies or no. I having speech with a Godly man lately about these, he would have them called re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, which if it be admitted, I doukt we shall rush upon a rock; for if they were religious, I see not but we must acknowledge as much of the Altar, and if so, then may the Church constitute such ceremonies: for I should be loath to condemne the judgement of the whole Church (especially in those purer times) in allowing of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> That which maketh a ceremony religious is not all
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:168930:22"/>use of it in time of divine worship, no nor allways the use of it to a religious end. A child or servant sitteth barehead in time of divine worship, &amp; yet his gesture of reverence is civil. The bell ringeth to a Sermon, which end is religious, yet the action is civil; but I conceive it. 1. The setting apart of a ceremony to God or to his worship maketh it holy and religious, <hi>Lev.</hi> 27.28.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The using of it directly, and immediately to a spiritual or religious end maketh it also spirituall and religious. The ringl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a bell directly and immediately calleth the people together, that they beeing met, joyne in spirituall duties ariseth by virtue of an higher call.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now a ceremony is imployed to a religious end, when it is used,</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>To teach some spirituall doctrine, as when images are used for lay mens bookes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>To stire up devotion, or quicken and strengthen spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall affection, and graces, as the sacrament and abusive popish confirmation.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>To prevent and drive away impediments of Spiritual devotion, as holy-water and the Crosse amongst the Papists, to cleanse from veniall sinns, and to drive away devils.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Altar on this side <hi>Jordan</hi> did directly and immediately expresse onely a similitude of the Altar before the ark, and so by consequent implyed that the fashion of the Altar before the arke was not unknown to the <hi>Reubenites</hi> and <hi>Gadites,</hi> and by a further consequent implyed that they had been wont to see the altar before the ark and to worship at it? But this use of the altar was only civil, as the ringing of a bell to a Sermon. The philacteries were religious for being commanded of God to a religious end, directly and immediately (to wit) to put them in mind of Gods commandments, that they might not look besides them, nor seek after their own hearts, and eyes, <hi>Num.</hi> 15.38, 39. They doubtlesse had a spirituall efficacy to help forward these ends.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>